Grant Wythoff

Center for Digital Humanities wythoff.net

Princeton University twitter.com/gwijthoff
Firestone Library (856) 296-9103

Princeton, NJ 08544 gwythoff@princeton.edu

Trained in literary history, I study technology: the cultural lives of tools and techniques. Combining perspectives from media theory and digital humanities, my research involves theoretical speculation, hands-on practice, and historical and technical description. I am currently thinking about the resilience of infrastructures, users, and communities.

Areas of Expertise

- · Open-Source Scholarship, Minimal Computing, History of Method in the Humanities
- Tech Ethics, Algorithmic Inequality, Public Sphere Theory
- Networked Selfhood, Data Privacy, User Culture, Distraction, Tacit Computing
- History & Philosophy of Technology, Media Archaeology, Infrastructure & the Future
- American Literature, Science Fiction, Early Cinema

Appointments

2019-present PRINCETON UNIVERSITY

Digital Humanities Strategist

Princeton, NJ

2017–2019 PENNSYLVANIA STATE UNIVERSITY

Visiting Fellow, Center for Humanities and Information

State College, PA

2013–2017 COLUMBIA UNIVERSITY

Postdoctoral Fellow, Society of Fellows in the Humanities Lecturer, Department of English and Comparative Literature

New York, NY

Education

English Literature, Ph.D

Princeton University, Princeton, NJ

2009 Media and Modernity, Certificate

Princeton University, Princeton, NJ

English Literature, B.A., Summa Cum Laude

Publications

Books

2016

in progress Gadgetry: A User's Guide to Technique in the Age of Tech

selected for workshopping at Object Lessons / NEH Institute on public academic writing and the Center for American Literary Studies First Book Institute

The Perversity of Things: Hugo Gernsback on Media, Tinkering, & Scientifiction University of Minnesota Press 384pp, 146 b&w illustrations

- Research Society for American Periodicals Book Prize, honorable mention
- Selected Reviews: New York Review of Books

 Leonardo

 Science Fiction Studies

 American Literary History

 Year's Work in Critical/Cultural Theory

ACADEMIC ARTICLES

2020	"Extended Technique: New Scholarship on the Uses of Media" <i>Amodern</i> , issue 9
2018	"Laptop Policy: Notes on Boredom" Digital Humanities Quarterly, Vol. 12, No. 2
2018	"On Method in the Humanities" Configurations, Vol. 26, No. 3
2016	"Design and DH in the Media Studies Classroom" Cinema Journal Teaching Dossier, Digital Humanities and Media Studies Crossovers issue
2015	"Artifactual Interpretation" Journal of Contemporary Archaeology, Vol. 2, No. 1
2015	"The Form of Content Delivery" Media Fields Journal
2014	"Areophone, Telephot, Hypnobioscope: Hugo Gernsback & the Science Fictionality of Media" Wi: Journal of Mobile Media
2014	"Sustainable Authorship in Plain Text Using Pandoc and Markdown" <i>The Programming Historian</i> , with Dennis Tenen. Spanish transl. by Víctor Gayol as "Escritura sostenible en texto plano usando Pandoc y Markdown"
2013	"Learning with Polyphony: AmpDamp" iConference 2013 Proceedings, pp. 1090-1094, with A. Acker et al.
2013	"Pocket Wireless and the Shape of Media to Come, 1899-1922" Grey Room, 51, pp. 40-63

PUBLIC WRITING

"Silicon Valley is Ready to Make Your Decisions For You"

The Washington Post, Sun Aug 19, p. B3

2017 "Public Enemies"

Real Life Magazine

2014 "The Invention of Wireless Cryptography"

The Appendix

"Like Holding the Future In Your Hands: The Gadget at CES 2011"

In Media Res: A Media Commons Project

"There are eight million stories in the naked city; this has been one of them': Procedurality

and The Naked City"

In Media Res: A Media Commons Project

BOOK REVIEWS

"Review of Matthew Kirschenbaum, Track Changes: A Literary History of Word Processing"

Revista Hispánica Moderna, Vol. 71, No. 1

"Review of Patrick Jagoda, Network Aesthetics"

American Literary History Online Review, Series XV

Teaching

Fall 2020 Privacy, Publicity, and the Text Message

undergrad seminar • Princeton University

Spring 2019 Networked Selfhood and the Novel

undergrad seminar • Bryn Mawr College

Fall 2018 Tacit Media and Digital Culture

grad seminar • Penn State University

Spring 2018 Global Science Fiction

undergrad lecture • Penn State University

Spring 2017 Introduction to Digital Media

undergrad lecture • Columbia University

Spring 2016 The Science of Fiction: American Naturalism, 1880-1940

undergrad seminar •

Spring 2016 Digital Humanities Praxis

grad seminar • Columbia University

Spring 2014 Screen Reading: The History of Reading from Stone Tablet to Screen

undergrad seminar • Columbia University

Fall 2014 The Core Curriculum: Literature Humanities

undergrad seminar • Columbia University

Fall 2013 The Core Curriculum: Literature Humanities

undergrad seminar • Columbia University

Fall 2010 Intro to American Studies: American Places

Assistant Instructor • Princeton University

Spring 2010 Children's Literature

Assistant Instructor • Princeton University

Fall 2008
-Spring 2013

Teaching Fellow

Trenton Central, Ewing, and Princeton High Schools • Princeton University Preparatory Pro-

gram (PUPP)

Media Coverage

AMC Visionaries: James Cameron's Story of Science Fiction (US television miniseries, 2018)

Graham Johnson, "State of the Internet: Grant Wythoff," Are.na February 2018

Mars Hill Audio radio interview, February 2018

The Other Side of Mars, dir. Minna Långström (feature-length documentary, Finland, 2018)

Inventing the Future, dir. Eric Schockmel (documentary, 85min, Luxembourg, 2018)

Aurelio Cianciotta, "Edited by Grant Wythoff – The Perversity Of Things: Hugo Gernsback On Media, Tinkering, And Scientifiction," *Neural* (May 2017)

Kristen Gallerneaux, "Off the Shelf: Recommended Films, Fine Reads and Dot-coms," *The Henry Ford Magazine* (March-May 2017)

John DeNardo, "Learn More about the Creators of Science Fiction," *Kirkus Reviews* (February 2017)

Gregory L. Reece, "Hugo Gernsback and Perversity and Optimism at the Dawn of Science Fiction," *PopMatters* (December 2016)

Angelo Paura, "Hugo Gernsback, l'uomo che ci ha fatto innamorare del futuro," *Motherboard Italy* (November 2016)

Awards

2017

2013

2007

2018

2016

Research Society for American Periodicals (RSAP) Book Prize, Honorable Mention, for *The Perversity of Things: Hugo Gernsback on Media, Tinkering, and Scientifiction*

Microsoft Research FUSE Labs, Award for Best Social Media Expo Project for AmpDamp, a prototype "volume knob" for social media streams

The Jordan Lee Flyer Honors Award for best undergraduate thesis, Becoming-Film: A Brief Poetics of Trailers

Grants

Teaching Transformation and Innovation Grant, Schreyer Institute for Teaching Excellence, to support workshop series "Data Privacy, Democracy, and The Humanities"

Barr Ferree Publication Fund, Princeton University Department of Art and Archaeology, subvention in support of *The Perversity of Things: Hugo Gernsback on Media, Tinkering, and Scientifiction*

2015	Grants from centerNET and Consortium of Humanities Centers and Institutes (CHCI) to attend the New Scholars Seminar in Digital Humanities at the University of Western Sydney
2014	Columbia Center for Science and Society Course Development Grant for lecture course The Science of Fiction: American Naturalism, 1880-1940
2014	Center for American Literary Studies at Penn State University stipend to attend the First Book Institute
2013	Microsoft Research FUSE Labs travel grant to attend iConference 2013
2012	Mellon Foundation Officer's Grant, Scholarly Communications and Information Technology Program to support the development of the Princeton Prosody Archive
2012	Annan Dissertation Fellowship to support advanced dissertation research
2012	Princeton Program in American Studies Summer Prize to support research at the Hugo Gernsback Papers, Syracuse University Library Special Collections
2011	Nineteenth-Century Scholarship Online (NINES) Scholarship to attend the Digital Humanities Summer institute in Victoria, British Columbia
2008	Princeton Institute for International and Regional Studies Award for intensive summer language study in German
	Presentations
	Invited Public Lectures
2018	Visiting Faculty, Princeton/Weimar Summer School for Media Studies Princeton University, June
2018	Keynote at the Rutgers Camden Archive of Digital Ephemera (R-CADE) Symposium Rutgers University, Camden, April
2018	Media Inventories of the Nineteenth Century Dartmouth College, March
2017	Guest lecture in Mara Mills's graduate seminar, "Media Archaeology" New York University, March
2015	Workshop on the Game Boy Camera and Printer, Rutgers-Camden Archive of Digital Ephemera (R-CADE) Rutgers University, Camden, April
2015	"Hugo Gernsback and American Science Fiction," Paleofuturism symposium University of Louisville, April
2015	"The Perversity of Things: Scientifiction and Theories of Media c. 1920," Circuit, Current, Connection Symposium Penn State Center for American Literary Studies (CALS), February
2014	"The Ethics of Plain Text," with Dennis Tenen, Princeton/Weimar Summer School for Media Studies

"Mobile Media and the Paleolithic," Columbia Center for Archaeology

"From Marlinspike to Mobile Media: An Archaeology of the Gadget"

Princeton University, June

Columbia University, March

2014

2013

	Workshops
2018	Pathways with a PhD: DH Jobs, On and Off the Tenure Track Center for Digital Humanities, Princeton University, November
2018	Intro to Markdown, Pandoc, & GitHub, "Software in the Humanities & Social Sciences" series Penn State, March
2017	Object Lessons, NEH Institute on public writing $Tempe, AZ$, November
2016	Workshop on new website for CHCI Medical Humanities Summer Institute Kings College London, June
2015	New Scholars Seminar in Digital Humanities Digital Humanities (DH), Sydney, June
2014	First Book Institute Center for American Literary Studies, Pennsylvania State University, June
2013	New Media in American Literary History Northeastern University, December
2013	Microsoft FUSE Labs Social Media Expo iConference 2013, University of North Texas, February
2012	THATCamp Theory Rutgers University, New Brunswick, October
2012	Research Fellow at Values in Design Workshop University of California, Irvine, August
2012	Princeton / Weimar Summer School for Media Studies Princeton University, June
2011	Outside-the-Box Text Analysis Workshop Digital Humanities Summer Institute, University of Victoria, June
2011	Demo Session for the Princeton Prosody Archive NINES/NEH Summer Institute, University of Virginia, May
	Conferences
2018	"Unthinkable Expertise" Society for Science, Literature, and the Arts (SLSA), Toronto, November
2018	"Techniques and Technologies: On the Cultural History of the Gadget" Information & Humanities Conference, Pennsylvania State University, September
2018	"Tacit Computing and Method in the Humanities" Digital Humanities (DH), Ciudad de México, June
2017	Roundtable: Science Fiction as Protest Society for Literature, Science, and the Arts (SLSA), Tempe, AZ, November
2017	"Media Archaeology and Prehistory"

	Information & Humanities Conference, Pennsylvania State University, September
2016	"On Method in the Humanities" Society for Literature, Science, and the Arts (SLSA), Atlanta, November
2016	"Making Science in the Pulps" Society for Cinema and Media Studies (SCMS), Atlanta, March
2015	"Reading Middle Distance: A Cultural History of Tools and Techniques" Modern Language Association (MLA), Vancouver, January
2014	"Mobile Media and the Paleolithic" Archaeologies of Media and Film, University of Bradford, UK, September
2014	"Mobile Media and the Paleolithic," panel on "New Apparatus Theory" Society of Literature, Science, and the Arts (SLSA) Europe, Turin, Italy, June
2014	"Screen Reading," panel on Little Data: Old and New Media American Comparative Literature Association (ACLA), New York, March
2013	"Mechanical Vaudeville: Relaying the Great War through the American Science Magazines" The Great War and the Illustrated Press, Université de Paris-XIII, June
2013	"Pocket Wireless and the Shape of Media to Come, 1899-1920" Modern Language Association (MLA), Boston, January
2012	"Pocket Wireless and the Shape of Media to Come, 1899-1920" Material Culture Symposium for Emerging Scholars, Winterthur Museum at the University of Delaware, April
2012	"Pocket Wireless and the Shape of Media to Come, 1899-1920" Tufts University Graduate Humanities Conference, New York, February
2012	"Pocket Wireless and the Shape of Media to Come, 1899-1920" nstrument, Image, Ekphrasis: Intersecting Genres of Knowledge. SUNY Stony Brook, Manhattan, February
2012	"Collections and Communities: Building the Princeton Prosody Archive" Mid-Atlantic Archives Conference (MARAC), Cape May, NJ, April
2011	"Prosody and the Archive / Prosody as an Archive" Maryland Institute for Technology in the Humanities (MITH), December
2011	"Areophone, Telephot, Hypnobioscope: Gernsback and the Science Fictionality of Media" Media Histories: Materiality, Temporality, Epistemology, Columbia University, March
2010	"The Form of Content Delivery: Networked Content and Narrative Property" Critical Themes in Media Studies, The New School, New York, April
2009	"Projecting Martian Photography" Science Fiction Research Association (SFRA), Georgia Tech, June
2009	"Projecting Martian Photography" Projection: Speculating on Presence, Absence, and Nonsense, City University of New York, March
	Conferences Organized
2018	Invited curator for the Rutgers Camden Archive of Digital Ephemera (R-CADE) Symposium Rutgers University, Camden, April
2016	Insuetude: Conversations in Technological Discard and Archaeological Recuperation <i>Columbia University</i> , April

On Method in the Humanities

Heyman Center for the Humanities, Columbia University, Fall-Spring

2010 "Virtuosity," Princeton Americanist Research Symposium

Princeton University, March

2009 On the Possibility of Worlds: An Interdisciplinary Conference

Princeton University, March

PANEL CHAIR OR COMMENTATOR

"Artifactual Interpretation: Practices of the Material Turn"

Modern Language Association (MLA), Vancouver, January

A Critical Dialogue on Media and Materiality

with Bernhard Siegert and Ben Kafka, Columbia University, March

Social Ecologies panel, Scientific (R)evolutions
Rutgers University, New Brunswick, February

Service

Professional Service

Reviewer, NEH Coronavirus Aid, Relief, and Economic Security (CARES): Cultural Organizations, May 2020

Research Associate, Library of Congress Radio Preservation Task Force

Article manuscript reviewer for Digital Humanities Quarterly

Book manuscript reviewer for Wiley Blackwell's Media Studies list

Article manuscript reviewer for New Media and Society

Advisory Board member for thresholds: a digital journal for criticism in the spaces between

Manuscript reviewer for *Breakthrough Ideas* track, International Conference on Information Systems 2014 (ICIS 2014)

University Service

2019-present	Convener, Princeton University Humanities Computing Curriculum Committee (HC3)
2014-2017	Co-founder and Moderator, Group for Experimental Methods in the Humanities
2011-2013	Steering Committee Member, Princeton University Digital Humanities Initiative
2009-2013	Project Manager, Princeton Prosody Archive
2009-2010	Co-Chair, Americanist Research Colloquium, Princeton University

Professional Affiliations

Modern Language Association (MLA)

Society for Cinema and Media Studies (SCMS)

Society for Literature, Science, and the Arts (SLSA)

American Studies Association (ASA)

Science Fiction Research Association (SFRA)

American Comparative Literature Association (ACLA)

Research Society for American Periodicals (RSAP)

Tools and Techniques

Programming Languages: Python, shell scripting

Python Libraries: Beautiful Soup, NLTK

Markup Languages: TEI/XML, JSON, YAML, LaTeX, markdown

Web Development: Reclaim Hosting, HTML/CSS, Tachyons, Hugo, Jekyll, WordPress,

Omeka, Drupal, Scalar

Digital Mapping: QGIS, Leaflet, Google Earth

Security: PGP

Other Technologies: GitHub, SQLite, Scrivener, Zotero, Mendeley, Zapier, Notion,

Figma, Prezi, Microsoft Office, Apple iWork, iMovie

Languages

English (native)

German (reading proficiency and moderate speaking proficiency)

French (reading proficiency)